<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"><channel><title>Fermented Artistry</title><atom:link href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><link>http://www.fermentedartistry.com</link><description>Celebrating Craft Beer as Art</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 May 2012 15:24:09 +0000</lastBuildDate><language>en</language><sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod><sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency><generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=3.3.2</generator><xhtml:meta xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" name="robots" content="noindex" /><item><title>Learn to Homebrew With Fermented Artistry !</title><link>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/home-brew/learn-to-homebrew-with-fermented-artistry/</link><comments>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/home-brew/learn-to-homebrew-with-fermented-artistry/#comments</comments><pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2012 15:24:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Brad</dc:creator><category><![CDATA[Events]]></category><category><![CDATA[Home Brew]]></category><guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.fermentedartistry.com/?p=923</guid><description><![CDATA[]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/LearnToHomebrew_0011.jpg"><img class=" wp-image-925 alignleft" title="LearnToHomebrew" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/LearnToHomebrew_0011.jpg" alt="" width="490" height="648" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded><wfw:commentRss>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/home-brew/learn-to-homebrew-with-fermented-artistry/feed/</wfw:commentRss><slash:comments>0</slash:comments></item><item><title>Stout-a-Mania Chocolate Espresso Chili</title><link>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/food/stout-a-mania-chocolate-espresso-chili/</link><comments>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/food/stout-a-mania-chocolate-espresso-chili/#comments</comments><pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2012 22:17:07 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Brad</dc:creator><category><![CDATA[Food]]></category><guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.fermentedartistry.com/?p=903</guid><description><![CDATA[This weekend I wanted to feature a good friend of mine who not only loves craft beer but is an amazing cook! His name is Carlo Palumbo;  he and his family own and run several fine Italian restaurants in the central Pennsylvania region and love to mix the experience of great food and drink. I ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_906" class="wp-caption alignright" style="width: 310px"><a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/DSC_01371.jpg"><img class=" wp-image-906" title="Stout-a-Mania Chili" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/DSC_01371-300x209.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="209" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Photo By: Kara Moyer Photography</p></div>
<p>This weekend I wanted to feature a good friend of mine who not only loves craft beer but is an amazing cook! His name is Carlo Palumbo;  he and his family own and run several fine Italian restaurants in the central Pennsylvania region and love to mix the experience of great food and drink. I highly recommend if you ever come to the Harrisburg, Pennsylvania region you stop by DaVinci&#8217;s and order a plate of the smoked chicken and cheese ravioli, you will not be disappointed! Well with further adieu here is what Carlo cooked up for us this week&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8220;When I was going through my beer cellar I noticed I had a lot of stouts sitting around, so what better way to do a little spring cleaning than to have a stout theme party for the upcoming Wrestle Mania 29. I figured let&#8217;s not just drink our stouts but rather cook with them as well! Some of the items that made to to the menu were chocolate stout chili, stout cheese dip with soft pretzels, and pulled pork glazed with a bourbon barrel aged stout. In everyone&#8217;s opinion the chili was the highlight of the evening, and Brad asked me to write up and share the recipe with you since it was such a hit.</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Tasting Notes:</strong></span></p>
<p>Right out of the pot this baby has a nice cinnamon, bakers chocolate, and chipolte aroma. Upon hitting your tongue it starts off sweet and chocolaty, and then the heat kicks in quickly. Thick and robust this is best served with corn bread and of course a malty beverage. This is a new twist on a old style of chili, and went over great with everyone at the party. My recommendations of beers that pair well with this are amber lagers and bocks. The bready sweet malts compliment the chocolate and help cool the burn that the peppers throws at you.</p>
<p>Being Italian in heritage I found this quote very fitting not only for enjoying a great meal but also enjoying some great beers as well:</p>
<p><em>“The best part of beer and food is the fun times and the memories you share with family and friends.”</em></p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Stout-a-Mania Chili</strong></span></p>
<p><em>Serves approximately 6-8 people and this is the scaled down version from our party.</em></p>
<p>Olive Oil</p>
<p>1 large vidalia onion, diced</p>
<p>4 lbs of chuck steak or stew meat, in 1/2 in. cubes</p>
<p>4 links of Chorizo sliced into coins</p>
<p>1 can red kidney beans</p>
<p>3 28oz cans of tomato, crushed or diced (I use one with garlic in it)</p>
<p>1 can of chipolte peppers in adobo sauce (slice or blend before adding)</p>
<p>1 bottle of chocolate stout (I used Brooklyn Chocolate Stout)</p>
<p>2 squares of quality unsweetened chocolate</p>
<p>2 tablespoons brown sugar</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Spice Blend:</strong></span></p>
<p>2 tablespoons of chili powder or more to taste</p>
<p>1 tablespoon of ground cayenne pepper</p>
<p>1 teaspoon of paprika</p>
<p>2 tablespoons of ground cumin</p>
<p>1 tablespoon of  finely ground espresso coffee</p>
<p>1 teaspoon of  ground cinnamon</p>
<p>1 tablespoon of kosher salt and pepper or more to taste</p>
<p>1 teaspoon garlic powder</p>
<p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Garnish Options:</span></strong></p>
<p>Sour cream</p>
<p>Shredded cheddar cheese</p>
<p>Chopped green onion</p>
<p>Serve with cornbread</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Variations:</strong></span></p>
<p>Fresh jalapenos</p>
<p>Diced bell peppers</p>
<p>Substitute a can of tomatoes for diced fresh tomatoes</p>
<p>Minced fresh garlic, if you did not purchase cans with garlic in them</p>
<p>Chicken or beef broth instead of a can of tomatoes</p>
<p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Beer Pairings:</span></strong></p>
<p>Amber Lager, Bocks, Double Bocks, or just get two chocolate stouts and drink the second one</p>
<p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Directions:</span></strong></p>
<p>1) I started off with a big pot and did this on a stove with medium heat. You can use a Dutch oven or crock pot, just adjust it the best way to your equipment. Start off by coating the bottom of the pot with olive oil. Add the diced onions and simmer until tender. <em>*note if you add peppers from the optional ingredient list, add now, and if adding fresh garlic, add right before tender*</em>. You can add the meat with the onions or it can be browned in a side pan to be drained of the juices. If you add the meats into pot you will just have to cook it a little longer when you add the tomato cans, but it will add nice caramelized flavor.</p>
<p>2) Once the meats are browned and the onions are tender, add the cans of tomatoes, can of chipotle peppers, and beer. Make sure to turn the heat  down a little bit. Stir and partially cover with a lid or plate and let cook down for about 2-3 hours stirring occasionally. This would be a good time to drain the beans into a colander, get the spice blend ready, and enjoy a beer.</p>
<p>Once you start smelling chipolte in the air and the mixture looks like it’s getting thicker, add the spice blend, brown sugar, and chocolate  (be sure to stir well to melt chocolate) and taste. If needed, add more spices to flavor,  but remember it will still cook down and the flavors will meld over time, so don’t go crazy.</p>
<p>3) Let cook for another 20 minutes then add beans.</p>
<p>4) Cook for about 20 more minutes to make sure beans are tender.</p>
<p>5) Once you get the chili to a thick consistency that you like, pull off stove. You can serve right away, or let cool then refrigerate overnight. Use garnishes and serve with corn bread.</p>
<p>6) Enjoy!</p>
]]></content:encoded><wfw:commentRss>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/food/stout-a-mania-chocolate-espresso-chili/feed/</wfw:commentRss><slash:comments>0</slash:comments></item><item><title>Beer Enthusiast or Beer Elisit?</title><link>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/beer-reviews/beer-enthusiast-or-beer-elisit/</link><comments>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/beer-reviews/beer-enthusiast-or-beer-elisit/#comments</comments><pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 13:21:48 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Brad</dc:creator><category><![CDATA[Bars & Taverns]]></category><category><![CDATA[Beer Reviews]]></category><category><![CDATA[Home Brew]]></category><guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.fermentedartistry.com/?p=879</guid><description><![CDATA[Welcome back, this week I wanted to talk about a topic that is really becoming a hot issue in the craft beer scene. No, it&#8217;s not the latest trending style or newest brewery you need to try it&#8217;s about being a responsible and well mannered craft beer enthusiast. As with everything in life, people form ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back, this week I wanted to talk about a topic that is really becoming a hot issue in the craft beer scene. No, it&#8217;s not the latest trending style or newest brewery you need to try it&#8217;s about being a responsible and well mannered craft beer enthusiast. As with everything in life, people form there own opinions and feelings towards things but when it specifically hits the craft beer world in a negative way, we as supporters tend to take it personally. So have you ever been out at your favorite bar or brewery and you see a table of people drinking and some patrons will have a big and burly beer style in there hand and the others will have a lighter more palatable offering and those people get hassled by the group? I am willing to bet we all have seen or been that person at one time or another and this is exactly what I am talking about, The infamous &#8220;Beer Elitist&#8221;. So what classifies a beer snob or a &#8220;elitist&#8221; ? Websters defines an elitist  as<em> &#8220;(of a person or class of persons) considered superior by others or by themselves, as in intellect, talent, power, wealth, or position in society&#8221;</em>. I think the key phrase  in that definition is<em> &#8220;or by themselves&#8221;</em> because these are the craft beer drinkers out there who are quick to mention they only drink certain types or styles of beer and tend to enjoy belittling others who don&#8217;t drink or coincide with their own beer choices. In our opinion drinking beer (craft or non) is a inclusive social event that should be revealed as fun. Not a stressful way to collect and guzzle as many rare beers as you can then tell others you&#8217;re  not a real beer connoisseur because you haven&#8217;t had them.</p>
<p>I reached out to some local beer writers in the area and wanted to get their opinion on what being a enthusiast or elitist meant to them. So, generously they each sent a nice response on the topic and I wanted to share them all with you. Our first entry is from Tierney who is a local beer and scene writer for her personl blog called <a href="http://stoutsandstilettos.wordpress.com/">Stouts &amp; Stilettos</a> . She is one of the coolest beer chicks around who knows her stuff, so be sure to support her blog as well! Here is what Tierney had to say:</p>
<p><em><a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/431692_611083163004_72300974_32084826_804633440_n.jpg"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-880" title="431692_611083163004_72300974_32084826_804633440_n" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/431692_611083163004_72300974_32084826_804633440_n-192x300.jpg" alt="" width="192" height="300" /></a> &#8220;My thoughts on the beer hysteria are both positive and negative. As a female craft beer drinker and supporter, I am excited about the amount of growth and notoriety the industry has seen over the past few years, especially among other women. The amount of new craft beer drinkers, breweries, brew pubs, and beers has been increasing exponentially, and that&#8217;s something to be proud of. My younger brother just turned 21 a few weeks ago and I noticed he had a picture of himself drinking a Magic Hat #9 without any influence from me. My generation is catching on and it&#8217;s awesome! Distribution is expanding, the community is growing, market share is exceeding all previous years, and honestly I&#8217;m pumped.</em></p>
<p><em>On the other hand, there&#8217;s a bitter side to the whole scene. The growth that most of us are seeing as an extreme positive for the entire industry isn&#8217;t being accepted across the board. That Magic Hat #9 I mentioned earlier is easily snubbed by many in the community. Instead of shared enthusiasm for a peer who decides to take the baby steps into craft, many are met with snobbery of those who are &#8216;beyond&#8217; that beer. Even worse are those who make snide comments towards those who just happen to be holding a Miller Lite in their hand instead of whatever it is that particular &#8216;expert&#8217; thinks they should be drinking. Worst of all is ever-expanding state of elitism towards certain rare beers and breweries, which are of course exceptional to all who have had the opportunity to enjoy them. A smaller beginning brewery gets bashed because their beers aren&#8217;t living up to the comparison to a larger more established brewery. Sometimes I think the entire community should take a step back and appreciate how far it&#8217;s come, welcome the new growth, and be encouraging those on the outskirts just looking for someone to take them under their wing and help them find a great new beer to love.&#8221;</em></p>
<p>Our next writer Jeff is a traffic engineer that loves his beer, but more importantly trying new beer. He is a featured author on the website <a href="http://http://thebeercircle.com/">The Beer Circle</a> and as a student at the University of Pittsburgh, Yuengling was his staple and the beginnings of liking something better than fizzy yellow water. This has evolved into an entire hobby, keeping a blog of all of the beers he tries and places he has traveled. Recently, Jeff has ventured into home brewing, and there is probably no saving him from being engulfed entirely by his love for craft beer. Here is what Jeff had to say:</p>
<p><em>&#8220;A beer snob to me is one who has lost all joy in showing people better beer. Instead of suggesting a beer that bridges the gap between macro and craft, this person <a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/406892_10100448395109543_14200818_50357996_1896672905_n.jpg"><img class="alignright  wp-image-897" title="406892_10100448395109543_14200818_50357996_1896672905_n" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/406892_10100448395109543_14200818_50357996_1896672905_n-200x300.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="317" /></a>instead sticks their nose up at a person drinking a Samuel Adams because it can be bought anywhere and the company has become too large. I recently experienced great joy in talking with my boss who likes good beer, but is very new to the scene. He said he tried “Dogfish Head’s version of Guinness.” While I knew he meant World Wide Stout, the two beers are not all that similar. However, it was great to hear a person try, and positively remember, a great beer. Never in the conversation did I correct him on the differences of the beer, I only confirmed the name of the beer he tried.</em></p>
<p><em>Personally, I just like to go out and enjoy beer, because after all, it is simply beer. Sure, I may run in to certain beers that I do not like or some disappointments in rarer beers, but that doesn’t mean that someone else’s palate is invigorated by that same beer. As humans, we are all different, and while we can collectively agree that certain beers are the best and worst, it doesn’t mean that someone else doesn’t like or deserve to try a beer. Opinions are valuable, but constant bombardment, either in the positive or negative direction, is the fastest way to turning a person away from the very thing you are advocating.&#8221;</em></p>
<p>I think Jeff and Tierney hit it right on the head,with one simple statement: &#8221; It&#8217;s just beer&#8221; and that&#8217;s all it was ever meant to me. Why do grown men and women try to lift there nose and hoard their secret stash of beers then trade them like Pokemon cards? Because the perception of fun in the hobby has obviously been lost for a long time. So this week I am sending you all off with some homework, go out and introduce a new beer to a friend and help them understand what our hobby is all about and why we choose to drink and respect craft beer in such a way. (Refrain from running your mouth about how you only drink rare beers and how people are dumb for choosing anything but craft etc&#8230;or how a beer is delicious &#8220;only if you never had it&#8221;) We beer enthusiast are a inclusive group of people not a exclusive club for certain members only. Well until next time&#8230;.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Name.jpg"><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-235" title="Name" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Name.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="161" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded><wfw:commentRss>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/beer-reviews/beer-enthusiast-or-beer-elisit/feed/</wfw:commentRss><slash:comments>0</slash:comments></item><item><title>Homebrew Gone Pro – Troegs Scratch 58 Mango Triple IPA</title><link>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/bars-and-taverns/homebrew-gone-pro-troegs-scratch-58-mango-triple-ipa/</link><comments>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/bars-and-taverns/homebrew-gone-pro-troegs-scratch-58-mango-triple-ipa/#comments</comments><pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2012 16:54:38 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Brad</dc:creator><category><![CDATA[Bars & Taverns]]></category><category><![CDATA[Events]]></category><category><![CDATA[Home Brew]]></category><guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.fermentedartistry.com/?p=874</guid><description><![CDATA[&#038;nbsp]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/eTCSCJ9YUTc" frameborder="0" width="560" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Name.jpg"><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-235" title="Name" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Name.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="161" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded><wfw:commentRss>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/bars-and-taverns/homebrew-gone-pro-troegs-scratch-58-mango-triple-ipa/feed/</wfw:commentRss><slash:comments>0</slash:comments></item><item><title>Traditional Kvass</title><link>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/home-brew/traditional-kvass/</link><comments>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/home-brew/traditional-kvass/#comments</comments><pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2012 16:02:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Brad</dc:creator><category><![CDATA[Home Brew]]></category><guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.fermentedartistry.com/?p=849</guid><description><![CDATA[So this week my brewing partner Mike and I wanted to kick it old school by trying to brew a traditional Russian Kvass. Yes you heard me right, now pronounce it to yourself like this: Kah-Vas and there you have it! So what exactly is a Kvass you say? Well here is a blurb I ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So this week my brewing partner Mike and I wanted to kick it old school by trying to brew a traditional Russian Kvass. Yes you heard me right, now pronoun<a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo5.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-852 alignright" title="Kvass Bread Mash" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo5-224x300.jpg" alt="" width="224" height="300" /></a>ce it to yourself like this: Kah-Vas and there you have it! So what exactly is a Kvass you say? Well here is a blurb I found about the style <em>&#8220;Kvass (a Russian word for leaven or yeast is one of the national alcoholic drinks of Russia, and popular also in Eastern Europe. It is made, by a simultaneous acid and alcoholic fermentation, of wheat, rye, barley and buckwheat meal, or of rye -bread, with the addition of sugar or fruit. It has been a universal drink in Russia since the 16th century. Though</em><em> in the large tow</em><em>ns it i</em><em>s made commercially, elsewhere it is frequently an article of domestic production. Kvass is of very low alcoholic content (0.7 to 2.2%) . There are, beside the or</em><em>dinary kind, superior forms of the drink, such as apple or raspberry.&#8221;</em></p>
<p>With a little research on traditional methods and typical flavors to expect we decided to give this a try and so far the results are looking great! When in doubt about a new brewing process I usually turn to Matt over at <a title="The Mad Fermentationist" href="http://www.themadfermentationist.com/">The Mad Fermentationist</a> for his plethora of knowledge of advanced homebrewing and barrel aging procedures. Upon reading his attempt to making this style we tweaked the initial recipe a little bit and added some raisins for authenticity. Here is our loose interpenetration of the Kvass we made.</p>
<p>1. Purchased 1.5 loaves of organic Jewish Rye bread from Whole Foods, then cut it into slices and toasted it in the oven at 300 degrees for 30 minutes.</p>
<p>2. Tore up the toasted s<a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo6.jpg"><img class="alignleft size-medium wp-image-853" title="Kvass Bread Runnings" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo6-224x300.jpg" alt="" width="224" height="300" /></a>lices and combined it with about 2 gallons of 170 degree water in Mike&#8217;s cooler mash tun, placed the lid on tight and let it rest for 24 hours.</p>
<p>3. The next day we pulled off all the hazy rye bread &#8220;wort&#8221; from the cooler and scooped out all the mushy bread into a strainer with cheese cloth lining it. We proceeded to squeeze the juice from the mush and added that to the sauce pan totaling about 1.5 gallons of rye bread &#8220;wort&#8221;.</p>
<p>4. Performed a small mash of Pilsner, Cara Brown, and Rye malts. Mashed in at 147 degrees with a 60 minute rest.</p>
<p>5. We heated up the bread &#8220;wort&#8221; up to 169 degrees and proceeded to use that as our sparging water hoping to filter out any chunks of soggy bread and maintain a nice low ABV.<a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo1.jpg"><img class=" wp-image-855 alignright" title="Kvass Sparge" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo1-224x300.jpg" alt="" width="224" height="300" /></a></p>
<p>6. Boiled only 30 minutes with one small hop addition (3/4 oz of Saaz) in the beginning of when the wort started rolling. 6oz of chopped raisins at 15 minutes left in the boil.</p>
<p>7. Chill and add oxygen as normal.</p>
<p>8. Pitched one packet of Red Star bread yeast (yes you heard me right, bread yeast)</p>
<p>9. Ferment at room temperatures.  <strong><em></em></strong><strong></strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo3.jpg"><img class="alignleft  wp-image-861" title="Kvass Fermenting" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/photo3-224x300.jpg" alt="" width="224" height="300" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>10. Enjoy! (Tasting notes to follow!)</p>
<p><em><strong>Original Gravity 1.038  = 8 Plato</strong></em></p>
<p><em><strong>Final Gravity = 1.008 = 2 Plato</strong></em></p>
<p><em><strong>3.19% ABV &amp; 6 IBU&#8217;s</strong></em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Name.jpg"><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-235" title="Name" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Name.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="161" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded><wfw:commentRss>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/home-brew/traditional-kvass/feed/</wfw:commentRss><slash:comments>0</slash:comments></item><item><title>Dogfish Head – Noble Rot</title><link>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/beer-reviews/dogfish-head-noble-rot/</link><comments>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/beer-reviews/dogfish-head-noble-rot/#comments</comments><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2012 01:16:10 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Brad</dc:creator><category><![CDATA[Beer Reviews]]></category><category><![CDATA[Saison / Farmhouse Ales]]></category><guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.fermentedartistry.com/?p=835</guid><description><![CDATA[Welcome Back! I hope you all are enjoying some unseasonably warm weather like we are having here in Central PA. This week we are once again taking another look at one of my favorite breweries; Dogfish Head. I know you might be thinking &#8220;Oh man another DFH review,  are they paying this guy to say ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome Back! I hope you all are enjoying some unseasonably<a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/DSC011964.jpg"><img class="alignright size-medium wp-image-845" title="Dogfish Head - Noble Rot" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/DSC011964-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="225" height="300" /></a> warm weather like we are having here in Central PA. This week we are once again taking another look at one of my favorite breweries; Dogfish Head. I know you might be thinking &#8220;Oh man another DFH review,  are they paying this guy to say this stuff!?&#8221; but I promise you my love for them is unconditional and true. As a real fan I am willing to admit the the last few beers they produced were off in my opinion, for example The Pearl Jam Twenty Tribute and Ta&#8217;henket. Yikes! I mean they were out in left field to what they normally put out. If you know anything about them they are always a little &#8220;off centered&#8221; as their motto states so you can imagine how wacky those were. Enough of the past let&#8217;s just focus on what we have today. So with great pleasure the featured beer of the evening is Dogfish Head &#8211; Noble Rot which weighs in at a hearty 9% ABV and hails from Milton, Delaware. To the Dogfish Head family this was looked at as Saison based fermentable project that meshes both wine and beer. Here is a brief description from their website on how the grapes were integrated into this beer. <em>&#8220;The first addition (of grapes) in the kettle was unfermented juice, known as must, from viognier grapes that have been infected with a benevolent fungus called botrytis. This noble rot reduces the water content in the grapes while magnifying their sweetness and complexity. The second addition is pinot gris must intensified by a process called dropping fruit, where large clusters of grapes are clipped to amplify the quality of those left behind.&#8221; </em>Something else I found interesting was that the grape must consist of 49% of the total batch making this the closest relative to wine without being the majority ingredient.  Anyway let&#8217;s start to work our way into this, I can&#8217;t wait any longer!</p>
<p><strong>Appearance:</strong></p>
<p>First off I want to point out that I love the new shaped 750ml bottles they got! A little sleeker in shape and they now come with the shark logo embossed into the neck of the bottle which is much classier looking. For my glass choice I went with a medium sized flute glass I picked up cheaply at Reading China and Glassware before my epic birthday beer tasting weekend. As I popped the cap off I was delighted to hear a loud sharp hissing noise come from the neck of the bottle and a thick cloud of carbonation gas hanging around the mouth. On the pour, I am getting a bright golden sunny yellow that is crystal clear. Almost like liquid sunshine with no haze or yeast floating around unlike a typical saison. When I was done there was a one finger thick bone white head that lingered for a little bit but after a few minutes it faded away to just a thin wisp around the edges of the glass. On the viscosity check I gave a quick swirl and only noticed a tiny amount of clinging on the walls and minimal legs creeping downward.</p>
<p><strong>Aroma:</strong></p>
<p>Wow, right of the start I am not even reminded of a beer but rather a fine white wine. Matter of fact I just bottled some Chardonnay I made last week and it has the same exact nuances to it. Loads of tart sugary white grapes, some pepper and grassy hops are faintly there in the finish. A touch of acidity around the edges that has some funk qualities to it but nothing like a true sour beer.</p>
<p><strong>Taste:</strong></p>
<p>Again, I am really surprised how winey this really is. Right out of the gate there are bready biscuit notes and light toast but, the dominant flavor are the white grapes. When you let it sit in your mouth for a second the &#8220;noble rot&#8221; kicks in and has a slight acidity on the sides of my tongue and makes me pucker put a little bit which I am enjoying a lot!  In the finish I can pull out some earthy, slightly spicy, and grassy hops that compliment and more importantly cut through all the sweetness in the grapes. The finish is crisp and dry making me want to come back for more and after each sip there is complexity building. I am officially a fan of this one!</p>
<p><strong>Drinkability:</strong></p>
<p>OK, as far as Dogfish Head goes this one is on the top of the list for easy drinking! Super complex and lots of wine flavors are mingling in between the thin beer lining. I would also be willing to say that this one would convince  lots of people who are not beer drinkers and make them a believer. Slightly fruity, mildly tart and acidic, but yet has that wonderful core of a traditional Belgian saison. This beer should be widely distributed throughout the country and priced pretty reasonably (I picked mine up for $13) so you should not pass this one by. Two big thumbs up from me (and my wife!) Well until next time&#8230;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Food Pairings:</strong>  Crab, Lobster, Gouda Cheese, Light Salads, Vanilla Ice Cream</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Name.jpg"><img class="alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-235" title="Name" src="http://www.fermentedartistry.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Name-150x150.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="150" /></a><strong>  Featured Links:</strong> <a href="http://www.dogfish.com">Dogfish Head Brewery</a></p>
]]></content:encoded><wfw:commentRss>http://www.fermentedartistry.com/beer-reviews/dogfish-head-noble-rot/feed/</wfw:commentRss><slash:comments>0</slash:comments></item></channel></rss>